Simone Centellegher

RESEARCHER · DATA SCIENTIST

Trento, Italy

My research interests focus on human behaviour understanding and in particular on the analysis of spending patterns from credit card transactions data, and social interactions and mobility patterns extracted from mobile phone data. Through this data and the use of statistical and machine learning methods, I can explore different facets of human behaviour.

Experience

Fondazione Bruno Kessler (FBK)

Trento, Italy

RESEARCHER AND DATA SCIENTIST IN THE MOBILE AND SOCIAL COMPUTING LAB (MOBS)

Mar. 2019 - current

Published several papers involving the study of social interactions extracted from phone calls, mobile phone GPS traces, spending
patterns from credit card transactions to study different aspects of human behaviour including psychological characteristics, human
mobility and spending behaviour.

Samsung Electronics Remote

RESEARCH CONSULTANT

Oct. 2019 - Dec. 2019

Designed a research plan to model and predict human behaviour from large-scale passively-collected data from mobile phone applications.

VodafoneLondon, United Kingdom

RESEARCHER AND DATA SCIENTIST INTERN

May. 2018 - Sep. 2018

Scaled and built new features to improve ML models using a dataset of customers with mobile phone data and mobile money transactions.

Advisors: Nuria Oliver · Giovanna Miritello

VodafoneLondon, United Kingdom

RESEARCHER AND DATA SCIENTIST INTERN

Jun. 2017 - Oct. 2017

• Cleaned, pre-processed and analyzed a dataset that included mobile phone data and mobile money transactions to understand customers' interaction patterns and to unveil relationships between communication and spending patterns. Built and developed models to predict spending behaviour.

Advisors: Nuria Oliver · Daniel Villatoro

MIT Media Lab

Cambridge Massachusetts IIS

VISITING SCHOLAR

Jul. 2016 - Aug. 2016

• Involved in a project related to the exploration of the relationship between income inequality and job automation. Advisor: Iyad Rahwan

Education

PhD in Information Engineering and Computer Science (cum laude)

Trento, Italy

University of Trento, Fondazione Bruno Kessler (FBK)

Nov. 2015 - Apr. 2019

• Thesis: Investigating individual traits, network dynamics and economic behavior using mobile phone data. Advisor: Bruno Lepri

BSc & MSc in Computer Science

Trento, Italy

University of Trento

Sep. 2008 - Jul. 2015

Skills

Programming Python · Pandas · Apache (Py)Spark · Java · SQL

Al Data Mining · Machine Learning

Libraries NumPy · Scikit-learn · xgboost · statsmodels

Languages English (C1) · Italian (Native)

Publications

Living in a pandemic: changes in mobility routines, social activity and adherence to COVID-19 protective measures.

Scientific reports

 ${\tt Lucchini\,L, \textbf{Centellegher\,S}, Pappalardo\,L, Gallotti\,R, Privitera\,F, Lepri\,B, De\,Nadai\,M.}$

2021

doi.org/10.1038/s41598-021-04139-1

Inferring psychological traits from spending categories and dynamic consumption patterns

EPI Data Science

Tovanich N, **Centellegher S**, Seghouani NB, Gladstone J, Matz S, Lepri B.

2021

doi.org/10.1140/epjds/s13688-021-00281-y

Mobile Money: Understanding and Predicting its Adoption and Use in a Developing Economy

roceedings of the ACM on IMWUT

CENTELLEGHER S, MIRITELLO G, VILLATORO D, PARAMESHWAR D, LEPRI B, OLIVER N.

2018

doi.org/10.1145/3287035

Personality traits and ego-network dynamics

PloS one

CENTELLEGHER S, LÓPEZ E, SARAMÄKI J, LEPRI B.

2017

doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0173110

The Mobile Territorial Lab: a multilayered and dynamic view on parents' daily lives.

EPJ Data Scienc

CENTELLEGHER S, DE NADAI M, CARAVIELLO M, LEONARDI C, VESCOVI M, RAMADIAN Y, OLIVER N, PIANESI F,

2016

PENTLAND A, ANTONELLI F, LEPRI B.

doi.org/10.1140/epjds/s13688-016-0064-6

Etsch: Partition-centric graph processing

CBDCom International Conference

GUERRIERI A, MONTRESOR A, CENTELLEGHER S.

2016

doi.org/10.1109/UIC-ATC-ScalCom-CBDCom-IoP-SmartWorld.2016.0115

Projects

GPS mobility for COVID-19

Onaoina

FBK

2020

Designed and developed a pipeline with Apache (Py)Spark on Azure cloud machines to process 7.5 TB of raw GPS data of 100M users.

- Users' stop locations computed from raw GPS data
- Nearest Point of interest (OpenStreetMap) associated to each stop location (if present)
- · Users' home and work locations detected

Industrial Projects

INTESA SAN PAOLO, INTERNATIONAL GAME TECHNOLOGY, DATAPOPALLIANCE

2016-2020

Involved in industrial projects with several organizations and companies using open and proprietary data.

- Analizing credit card transaction data to unveil possible relationships with health behavior
- Development of a model to understand the key drivers of the success of a game room from IGT data, census data and OpenStreetMap
- Investigating the risk factors of crime in Colombia

Personal blog Ongoing

HTTPS://SCENTELLEGHER.GITHUB.IO

2017

Personal page where I write on my research and on different topics such as machine learning, programming in Pandas and PySpark, and data visualization with Matplotlib (\sim 5K monthly unique users).

Other Activities

Reviewer Scientific Data · EPJ Data Science · PLOS One · Ubicomp